Register of the Percy Brown papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Percy Brown papers
1900-1967
88033
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (1.6 linear feet)
The Percy Brown papers consist of writings, newspaper articles, and photographs relating to Percy Brown, a photojournalist and author who photographed scenes of World War I from the front lines on the Western front. Also included is information on the Ruhleben prison camp in Germany where Brown was a prisoner of war for three years, and first-hand accounts of the rescue of the icebound Soviet ship Solovei in 1920.
Brown, Percy, 1885-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1885 March 9 Born in Shrewsbury, Shropshire, England
1906-1908 Worked in San Francisco, California, U.S.A as a carpenter after the 1908 Earthquake
1908-1914 Became a "professional rollerskating expert" at the Olympia Rollerskate Rink in London
1914-1915 Photographed scenes of World War I in Belgium and France
1915-1918 Captured by German counter-intelligence and sent to Ruhleben prisoner of war camp
1918-1919 Photographed the German Revolution in Berlin
1920 Snuck aboard the icebreaker Svyatogor as correspondent for The Daily Graphic en route to rescue the icebound Solovei
1922-1930 Worked as a photojournalist for The Daily Sketch
1934-1938 Owned and managed Royal Hotel in Portishead, England
1938-1948 Owned and managed Castle Lodge in Ludlow, England
1948 Left England for San Francisco, California; worked as a carpenter, doorman, photographer, and life insurance salesman.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into 6 series: Biographical Material; World War I; Solovei Rescue file; Writings; Newspaper Articles; and Photographs
Scope and Content of Collection
The Percy Brown papers consist of writings, newspaper articles, and photographs relating to Percy Brown, a photojournalist and author who photographed scenes of World War I from the front lines on the Western front. Also included is information on the Ruhleben prison camp in Germany where Brown was a prisoner of war for three years, and first-hand accounts of the rescue of the icebound Soviet ship Solovei in 1920. Much of the material centers on his writings, including diary entries and unpublished manuscripts, and on newspaper articles, both by Brown and others.
Ruhleben (Prison camp: Germany); Solovei; (Ship); Journalists.; Prisoners of war.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--Western Front.; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons.
- Biographical Material, 1925-1952 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- World War I, 1914-1945
  - Newspaper Articles, 1914-1945
    - Written by Brown, 1914-1945 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Written by others, 1915-1928 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - My Visit to Ruhleben by Bishop Bury, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Miscellany, 1914 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Solovei Rescue file, 1920
  - Maps, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Passenger and crew list, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Drafts, 1920
    - Interviews, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Correspondence, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Articles, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Newspaper articles, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Diary entries and notes, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Miscellany, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Writings, 1930-1960
  - Manuscripts, 1953-1960
    - Roller-skating, Practical and Theoretical, Its Origin, Development and Possibilities, 1953 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - The Golden Gate is Always Open, 1960 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Reviews, 1930-1945
    - Round the Corner, 1934-1937 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Almost in Camera, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Other books, 1930 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Correspondence from publishers, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Newspaper Articles, 1908-1967
  - Written by Brown, 1918-1952
    - Yugoslavian Royal Family, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Photojournalism, 1944-1949 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Other, 1918-1952 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Written by others, 1908-1967
    - About Percy Brown, 1933-1967 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Properties, 1937-1944 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - Clippings, 1908-1952 (Box-folder 2: 11)
- Photographs, 1900-1933
  - Pre-World War I Miscellaneous Portraits, 1900-1910 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - London Olympia Rollerskate Rink, 1908-1914 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - World War I, 1914-1918
    - Various France and Belgium, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Antwerp, 1914 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Front Lines and Trenches, 1914-1918 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Ruhleben prisoner of war camp, 1915-1918 (Box-folder 3: 6-7)
  - Rescue of the Solovei, 1920 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Post World War I, 1918-1933 (Box-folder 3: 9)